ARUN VARGHESE – SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Location: Plano, Texas Email: arunv4700@gmail.com
Phone: 469-777-0675 Website: https://avarghese.me

SUMMARY

Results-oriented and self-motivated with over seven years of industry experience in the complete SDLC of enterprise applications. Looking to expand scope of technical knowledge and contribute to the company's success. In my free time, I enjoy creating applications that demonstrate and further my aptitude in UI/UX and software architecture.

HIGHLIGHT OF QUALIFICATIONS

- √ 7+ years of java development experience using agile methodology
- ✓ Drive complex solutions and deliver on time while coordinating with cross functional teams
- ✓ Writes scalable and resilient code by utilizing emerging technology and researching latest software patterns
- Visualizes and designs systems across multiple product lines and integrations with external systems
- ✓ Proactively analyzes and recommends ways to reduce technical debt and automate repetitive tasks
- ✓ Strong technical and interactive communication skills, as well as excellent collaboration skills
- Exceptional at building trust and influencing decisions with business, vendors, and stakeholders
- ✓ Client-focused, with strong interest in working with new technologies to solve business problems
- ✓ Strong leadership skills with respect to influencing/mentoring team members and managing resources
- ✓ Able to adapt and be successful in handling multiple responsibilities in high-stress environments
- Experience in working on distributed systems and messaging patterns, as well as n-tiered architecture
- ✓ Efficiently able to break down technical problems to facilitate solutions

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages

Java/J2EE / Groovy / JavaScript ES5/ES6 / TypeScript / Shell Scripting / YML / XML

Source Control

Git / Gitflow / Github / Bitbucket / SVN / ClearCase

Frameworks & Architecture

Agile / Microservices / SOA / Spring Boot + MVC / REST / SOAP / Hibernate / Mean.IO / Kafka + Flink / Grails

Front End

JQuery / Angular 2.5/4 / AJAX / Bootstrap / Gulp / JSON / CSS3 / SCSS / HMTL5 / Markdown

Back End

JPA / GORM / MongoDB / Liquibase / Oracle 11g / SQL Server / Oracle SQL Developer / PL/SQL / JDBC / MyBatis

Server

Tomcat / Heroku / Nginx / RabbitMQ / Express

Testing

JUnit / FrisbyJS / Spock / Mockito / Selenium / Karma / Jasmine / Protractor / HermesJMS / Firebug

Build and Automation

Jenkins / Maven / Nexus / Gradle / Travis-CI / Docker / NPM / Bower / Bamboo / Sonar / FishEye / Crucible / Ant

Tools

IntelliJ / Eclipse / Postman / SoapUI / Chrome Dev Tools / Kafka Tool / Kibana / FluentD / Blue Ocean

Data Monitoring

Kafka Tool / Kibana / Fluentd / Splunk / Data Dog

Interests

Machine Learning / Mobile Development / Python / React 16 / AWS / Azure / Kubernetes

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Masergy Inc. – Plano, TX

June 2018 - Present

Senior Software Engineer & Technical Lead

Highlights & Responsibilities

- Decomposed company sales workflow by domains, took isolated contexts and migrated them to micro services that are a part of a new event driven messaging architecture
- Implemented versioned APIs and bounded contexts using DTOs and JPA to reduce dependencies, remove cross-schema communications, improve scalability, and properly define domains
- Leveraged front-end expertise to successfully migrate legacy application pages to Angular, thus reducing page load times, improving maintainability, and enriching the customer experience
- Designed and developed solution for persisting user application preferences through a micro service using a mongo data store; presented during company hackathon and was approved for implementation
- Organized lunch and learn on Angular practices, standards, and problems/solutions, providing the team with a collaborative atmosphere while increasing knowledge and promoting work culture

Technical Environment

Mac OS, Linux, Elastic Search, HTML, JQuery, AJAX, CSS, XML, MySQL, MyBatis, Mongo, JPA, DTO, IntelliJ, Micro Services, Agile, Scrum, Kanban, TDD, Karma, Selenium, Spring MVC, REST, OO, GIT, Cobertura, Nexus, Maven, Tomcat, JUnit, SoapUI, Postman, Slack, JIRA, Pivotal, MS PowerPoint/Word/Excel, Confluence Wiki, Splunk, AngularJS/Angular, TypeScript, JavaScript

Spireon Inc. – *Irving, TX*

August 2015 – June 2018

Senior Software Engineer & Scrum Master

Highlights & Responsibilities

- Built CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins and Blue Ocean, standardized processes across teams for automated promotion of code to high environments, effectively reducing total manual deployments
- Owned the development and successful rollout of SIM management features for new vendors/partners, which decreased device airtime costs up to fifty percent and support teams' involvement in the process
- Developed multiple scripts to allow production support teams to tackle high priority issues that were discovered during critical feature rollout, reduced manual support times drastically from 60 cases a day to less than 10
- Decomposed domains and redesigned services to support scaling of reporting abilities for our customer solutions as part of a push for a more microservice oriented architecture utilizing Spring Boot, Docker, Kafka, AWS, Flink
- Delivered microservice for pilot project, including solution design, implementation, integration, and production readiness
- Improved logging and data visualization capacity by leveraging Fluentd log driver, developed configurations to parse log streams and dynamically capture interesting key/value pairs in log statements
- Scrum Master, helped the team to develop consistent results and velocity using agile methodologies
- Initiated and led agile meetings including daily scrum, grooming, retrospectives, and planning sessions
- Partnered closely with the lead architects to influence and drive technology solutions
- Managed onboarding for new developers, including mentorship and best practices
- Worked with vendor integrations for M2M architecture while collaborating with external teams to drive delivery
- Led efforts to onboard new vendors, including knowledge share, API integration, and network configurations
- Migrated legacy code from previous code base, adhering to new coding standards and best practices
- Supported development initiatives to enhance core technology and improve customer experiences
- Created published scripts as workarounds to current application logic gaps

- Documented personal notes whenever possible, updating documentation gaps and onboarding guides as needed
- Created automated testing scripts to reduce rework and shorten test script authoring time for QA Teams
- Worked with major carriers to setup m2m services, upgrade APIs, and troubleshoot customer issues
- Presented on multiple occasions to upper management including functional demos and solution designs

Technical Environment

Mac OS, Linux, M2M, Groovy, Grails, Elastic Search, MongoDB, CXF, HTML, JavaScript, JQuery, AJAX, CSS, XML, MySQL, Agile, TDD, Spring MVC, REST, SOAP, OO, Git, Nexus, Maven, Tomcat, Spock, JUnit, SoapUI, Postman, Slack, JIRA, Pivotal, MS PowerPoint/Word/Excel, Confluence Wiki, Logic Monitor, Splunk, Angular, Kibana, Fluentd, Docker, Microservices, Blue Ocean

Fidelity Investments – Westlake, TX

July 2012 - August 2015

Software Engineer & Tech Lead

Highlights & Responsibilities

- Owned and maintained high visibility maturing application dealing with Reference Data Consolidation as well as supported over five other applications within the company's data access layer
- Led efforts in integrating with vendor-developed adapter to connect to systems for automating data setup, effectively reducing manual setup process from weeks to minutes
- Piloted disaster recovery automation efforts, utilized HP Operations Orchestration studio to create release processes to minimize manual inputs and reduce resources on call
- Developed well documented and extendable test suite using SoapUI/Postman for services, drastically reduced time spent on creating tests for new services
- Automated test data generation by incorporating real time data through Java code thus reducing testing timeframe and the number of code, scripts, and manual inputs required to complete E2E integration tests
- Identified issues with deployment process, learned and implemented UNIX shell scripts to automate deployment process in application environments to reduce deployment errors and overall execution time
- Interfaced with quality assurance team to develop a testing tool using Selenium and JUnit testing frameworks, used by both quality assurance and development team for extensive testing
- Took the initiative to write JUnits for projects with out any tests to improve Sonar nightly build reports, improved coverage from 0% to over 70%
- Facilitated quarterly releases using SAFe framework through collaborating with architecture leads
- Performed code reviews through FishEye/Crucible for developers to improve code quality and efficiency
- Reviewed change requests and collaborated with product owners to prioritize backlogs for releases
- Developed web services using both REST and SOAP to support DAL SDS application
- Worked with quality assurance team to document and prioritize defects documented in HP Quality Center
- Managed branching and merging of project source code in SVN to align with quarterly project releases

Technical Environment

Windows, Linux, Java/J2EE, HTML, JavaScript, JQuery, AJAX, CSS, XML/XSD, XSLT, Shell Scripting, Oracle 11g, Oracle SQL Developer, PL/SQL, JDBC, iBatis, MyBatis, Agile, TDD, Selenium, Spring MVC, REST, SOAP, SOA, OO, SVN, Bamboo, Sonar, FishEye/Crucible, Ant, Maven, SpringSource, Tomcat, WinSCP, Putty, JUnit, SoapUI, Postman, Selenium, JIRA, HP Quality Center, HP Operations Orchestration, HP Service Manager, MS PowerPoint/Word/Excel, SharePoint

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas

May 2012

ACHIEVEMENTS

Collaborator on US Patent 9491178 B2 Identifying a measure of online security

Published November 2016

During a three-day cyber security hackathon sponsored by Fidelity Investments, worked in a team to design and implement an algorithm used to generate a digital security score based on a composite of various weighted factors. The company saw this as a potentially significant IP, and collaborated with our team to submit the patent.